<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="//feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-16T20:12:26-07:00</updated><id>//</id><title type="html">Jacob West-Roberts</title><subtitle>Moon is a minimal, one column jekyll theme for your blog.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Week 1 Walkthrough- Intro to Bash</title><link href="//Week_5_walkthrough/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week 1 Walkthrough- Intro to Bash" /><published>2020-02-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-02-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>//Week_5_walkthrough</id><content type="html" xml:base="//Week_5_walkthrough/">&lt;h1&gt;Hello and welcome to week 1 of ESPM 112L-&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Metagenomic Data Analysis Lab!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tasks-for-today&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-tasks-for-today&quot;&gt;Tasks for Today&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1-what-is-the-command-line&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-1-what-is-the-command-line&quot;&gt;1. What is the command line?&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#interlude-for-those-intimidated-by-the-command-line&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-interlude-for-those-intimidated-by-the-command-line&quot;&gt;Interlude: For those intimidated by the command line&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2-how-do-i-access-the-command-line&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-2-how-do-i-access-the-command-line&quot;&gt;2. How do I access the command line?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#3-basic-commands&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-3-basic-commands&quot;&gt;3. Basic Commands&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#--ls&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc---ls&quot;&gt;- &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#--cd&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc---cd&quot;&gt;- &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#4-connecting-to-the-class-server&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-4-connecting-to-the-class-server&quot;&gt;4. Connecting to the class server&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ssh&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-ssh&quot;&gt;SSH&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#changing-the-password&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-changing-the-password&quot;&gt;Changing the password&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#5-creating-modifying-and-moving-files--directories&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-5-creating-modifying-and-moving-files--directories&quot;&gt;5. Creating, modifying, and moving files &amp;amp; directories&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#--pwd&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc---pwd&quot;&gt;- &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pwd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#--mkdir&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc---mkdir&quot;&gt;- &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mkdir&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#creating-and-deleting-files&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-creating-and-deleting-files&quot;&gt;Creating and deleting files&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#finishing-up&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-finishing-up&quot;&gt;Finishing up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week’s lab is going to be short and sweet, and include lots of links to external resources (for your reference now and after this class is done). There’s a lot of writing here, but there’s not too much actual work involved yet. That will come, don’t worry!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the terminal (also called the command line) is crucial for bioinformatics, among many other things, and this lab will lay the foundation for you to become proficient in using tools on the terminal. Before we get into how to access it on various operating systems, let’s discuss what it actually is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tasks-for-today&quot;&gt;Tasks for Today&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get your points for lab today, you’re going to have to register for an account on the class server, join a group, and send me your username/password combo as well as the names of your group members. Additionally, you’re going to make a directory and a few files as part of the tutorial - you’re going to send me the path to this folder as well. (More on that in a bit.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-what-is-the-command-line&quot;&gt;1. What is the command line?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The command line is an interface designed for you to navigate directories and view files on a computer. This is also called the terminal; it looks like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-y_Qcr6C4aTQ/UB5xcCxM3ZI/AAAAAAAABSk/29C-JeH68Nk/s1600/Pretty+Terminal+Mac.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-y_Qcr6C4aTQ/UB5xcCxM3ZI/AAAAAAAABSk/29C-JeH68Nk/s1600/Pretty+Terminal+Mac.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Example Terminal with Color Formatting&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the above example, you can see multiple types of commands, such as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt;. These are programs, included by default with unix systems such as Linux or Mac OSX. These programs are included as part of something known as a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;shell&lt;/code&gt;; in Unix distributions (and when downloaded on Windows) this shell is named &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bash&lt;/code&gt;, and on Mac OSX this is generally &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;zsh&lt;/code&gt;. (The difference between the two is unimportant for our purposes right now.) I’ll refer to the shell as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bash&lt;/code&gt; from here on out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of the tools we will use in this course are operated from the command line, just like these. In essence, what you’ll be doing is navigating around a file system just like you might on your own computer using Windows explorer or the Mac OSX finder. This method has several advantages, though, because of all the programs you’ll have access to which are best used on the command line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;interlude-for-those-intimidated-by-the-command-line&quot;&gt;Interlude: For those intimidated by the command line&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are certainly ways around using the command line for most applications. We will go over alternatives at every step of the way where possible, and if you find a good alternative to the command line for a particular task, feel free to use it! I and many other bioinformaticians feel most comfortable on the command line, and I feel it’s a valuable tool. But don’t stress out about it! You don’t need to use it for everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind also that I will provide specific examples on how to do most everything you’ll need to do on the command line for this course. And don’t panic if you run into errors- it’s a natural part of the process of working with these types of systems and data. It builds character, as they say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-how-do-i-access-the-command-line&quot;&gt;2. How do I access the command line?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will differ based on the operating system you’re using. Let’s divide this up into three categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linux (includes Chrome OS)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Press &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ctrl+Alt+t&lt;/code&gt; to open a terminal. Congratulations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mac OSX&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Click on the Spotlight Search icon (magnifying glass) at the top right corner of your screen. Search ‘terminal’, and open the application. I recommend pinning this to your dock/taskbar; you’ll be using it a fair bit.
Detailed instructions &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.howtogeek.com/682770/how-to-open-the-terminal-on-a-mac/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Windows&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Go to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/p/windows-terminal/9n0dx20hk701?activetab=pivot:overviewtab&quot;&gt;Windows store&lt;/a&gt; and download Windows Terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have trouble getting this working, let me know. It should be a fairly painless process in most instances, though, now that Windows has its own terminal! (That’s relatively new.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-basic-commands&quot;&gt;3. Basic Commands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First we’re going to want to do the things you’re used to doing in normal file explorers like OSX Finder or Windows Explorer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two most important commands are the ones you can see used in the example picture above: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;--ls&quot;&gt;- &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; is fundamental and super important. Short for the word ‘list’ (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ls#History&quot;&gt;proof&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; shows you the contents of a directory. Try it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://i.stack.imgur.com/k4EBH.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.stack.imgur.com/k4EBH.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Example usage of ls that I grabbed from google&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Advanced usage (not necessary, just fun)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; has many options that can change what it shows you and how that data is displayed. My favorite is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ls -thora&lt;/code&gt;, which will show all the files in your current directory including hidden files, sort by date modified, and present it to you in a different format than standard &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt;. Try it! For a full list of options, see the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; manual page by typing &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;man ls&lt;/code&gt; and pressing enter.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;--cd&quot;&gt;- &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; is probably the most common command you’ll use, and the easiest (in my opinion) to remember. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; stands for ‘change directory’. It just moves you from one folder to the next, exactly like clicking on a folder in a file explorer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; has the advantage of being able to navigate anywhere in one command if you give the full location of a directory; the most analogous function is in Windows explorer when you paste the location of a file in the top navigation bar. (If there is one on OSX let me know, I don’t use that.) Let’s wait a little bit to try that one out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-connecting-to-the-class-server&quot;&gt;4. Connecting to the class server&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The class server is a computer we’re using to host your data and perform computational tasks this semester. Each of you will register for an account today, and learn how to access it. Physically, it exists just off campus in the UC Berkeley data center on Hearst; luckily for you, we can access it from anywhere. Let’s go over how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ssh&quot;&gt;SSH&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SSH stands for ‘Secure Shell’. Remember how the terminal is also called a shell? We’re just going to be connecting to a new terminal session on the class server over the internet. This is one of two most important commands to remember for this class, so write it down somewhere and remember you can always come back here to see it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ssh username@class.ggkbase.berkeley.edu&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty simple! I will be giving out usernames in class, as well as telling you the default password. (Information security 101: Don’t give away passwords willy-nilly.) Once you’ve connected successfully, you’re going to need to change that default password.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;changing-the-password&quot;&gt;Changing the password&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The command to change your password is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;passwd&lt;/code&gt;. Type this, and you will see a prompt asking for your current password. Enter it, then enter the new password- then you’re done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-creating-modifying-and-moving-files--directories&quot;&gt;5. Creating, modifying, and moving files &amp;amp; directories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, now to take your fancy new terminal for a spin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you SSH into the class server, you’re automatically going to be in your home directory (&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/home/studentX&lt;/code&gt;, where X is your ID number). This is your personal workspace, for storing important files and doing whatever else you might need to do for the course. To see the full path, type the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pwd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;--pwd&quot;&gt;- &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pwd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pwd&lt;/code&gt; stands for &lt;strong&gt;p&lt;/strong&gt;rint &lt;strong&gt;w&lt;/strong&gt;orking &lt;strong&gt;d&lt;/strong&gt;irectory. It gives you the name of the folder you’re currently at, which is useful for moving files around and navigating quickly. The location of files and directories on the terminal is called the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PATH&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, let’s make a directory that we’ll work in for today. Call it whatever you like- if you’re not feeling creative, call it ‘tutorial’ or ‘sandbox’ or what have you. You can create a directory with the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mkdir tutorial&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;--mkdir&quot;&gt;- &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mkdir&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mkdir&lt;/code&gt; stands for, as you might have inferred, ‘make directory’. Pretty straightforward. You have to provide a name for this directory, though- ex.  &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mkdir tutorial&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we’re going to navigate into this folder- remember our old friend &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt;? Try it now-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd tutorial&lt;/code&gt; (or whatever you named it)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you’re here (welcome!) let’s try creating a file. It’ll be empty at first, but that’s okay. You can create files in bash like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;filename&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;creating-and-deleting-files&quot;&gt;Creating and deleting files&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating files is easy- just use the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; character, followed by the name of the file you’d like to create. (like so: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt; test.file&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;test.file&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This file will be empty unless you’re putting something in it. Also, if there’s a file with the same name as the one you’re trying to create, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; will overwrite that file- be careful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Removing files is also pretty simple, although removing directories is not (for good reason). To remove files, use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rm&lt;/code&gt;, like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rm test.file&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finishing-up&quot;&gt;Finishing up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, to finish the tutorial, and your lab for today. Let’s make a file in your directory called ‘hello_world.txt’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;hello_world.txt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we’re going to add some text to it, using only the command line!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, try this: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;echo &quot;I love science&quot;&lt;/code&gt;. See how it prints text to the terminal for you to read? Now we’re going to put that text in a file, using echo and the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; operator. Try this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;echo &quot;Hello world!&quot; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; hello_world.txt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="test" /><summary type="html">Testing!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Testing post</title><link href="//testpost/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Testing post" /><published>2020-02-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-02-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>//testpost</id><content type="html" xml:base="//testpost/">&lt;p&gt;Can I make a project post display properly? Let’s find out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="test" /><summary type="html">Just making sure everything works.</summary></entry></feed>
